Chris: Development environments
So, what are development environments and
how do we go about selecting an appropriate
development environment for different languages?
A development environment helps coders
to develop a program using a set
of processes and programming tools.
They provide an interface which supports
coders to write and test the code and
package the build so that it can be deployed.
Environment types can include structure-oriented,
toolkits, and language-centred types.
Leah: When choosing a developer environment
consideration should be given to:
• The experience level of coder
• The compatibility with the platform and language
• The productivity required
• Extensibility that may be needed
such as addition tools being needed
at a later stage of a given project.
Chris: Also, performance is important as it
will affect productivity, so for example a
larger integrated development environment
with a lot of plugins will slow things down.
Junior developers would most likely begin
with a text editor when working purely with
writing code, however once they are more
involved in bigger projects within a team,
it is more likely that they would use an
integrated development environment or IDE
Leah: Although a ‘text editor such’ as ‘Atom’,
could be used as a developer environment
for programming, the main environment that
would be used to write code would be an IDE.
They provide a single program which can be
used for all aspects of programming, which
would include several features for authoring,
compiling, debugging, and deployment software.
Some IDEs are designed for specific
programming languages, but there are also
ones that will support multiple languages.
Chris: So, let’s look at
what an IDE would include:
• Syntax highlighting -where the code keywords and
syntax errors will display as different colours
• Code completion – an auto-completion
feature which can help reduce errors
• Version control integration – where the IDE
communicates with the version control software
• Debugging –the functionality of a debug tool
Leah: Some IDEs may also provide support
for Code search which means it can search
for classes, functions, and variables etc.
and some have support for visual programming
where a language can be manipulated visually,
for example Scratch, an event-driven
block-based programming language.
Now let’s look at some common
examples of development environments
used for coding languages.
Chris: Microsoft Visual Studio – There are
two versions of this, one is a full IDE which
is commonly used for Microsoft .NET projects
and Microsoft languages; and the other
Visual Studio Code is a free text editor.
Both versions support the most popular languages
including PHP, JSON, JavaScript, C#, and Python.
Leah: Eclipse – This is the second
most popular IDE for Java development.
It contains a base workspace and an extensible
plug-in system for customising the environment.
Chris: Netbeans – An Apache IDE for Java, which
allows applications to be developed from modules.
Leah: IntelliJ - a popular open-source IDE
primarily designed for Java development
but also supports other languages such
as Python, Ruby, PHP, SQL, JavaScript
Chris: Sublime Text –a text editor
which supports C++ and Python
Leah: Notepad++ - an open-source text
editor which runs in the Windows environment
and supports 80 programming languages.
Chris: Atom –a free and open-source text
and source code editor which is based on
a framework that enables cross-platform
editing and supports many languages including
Python, C++, Ruby, Java, JavaScript.
Please check out our weblinks
to explore these in more detail.